Eugene F. Savage Papers
Eugene F. Savage Papers
1925-1966
Savage, Eugene Francis, 1883-1978.
1 linear ft.
Papers of the American painter, muralist, sculptor. Collection includes correspondence, photographs of the artist as well as of his work, writings.
149460
Biographical History
Eugene Francis Savage (1883-1978) was an American realist and surrealist painter known for his mural, genre, figure and landscape works. He studied at the American Academy in Rome, the Corcoran School of Art, and the School of the Art Institute of Chicago, and taught at Yale School of Fine Art.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Eugene F. Savage Papers consist of art projects, biographical material and writings.
Art projects includes correspondence about his projects as well as photographs of them.
Biographical material contains personal photographs of Savage as well as a photograph of the house in which he was born. More biographical material can be found in the Franklin County Courthouse file and in two Who's Who listings in the undated section of the Miscellaneous file.
Writings contains an original typescript of an essay entitled "The triumph of conation," accompanied by an original drawing portraying the theme of the work.
Arrangement of the Collection
Art projects are arranged chronologically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Painters; Savage, Eugene Francis, 1883-1978.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Mural painting and decoration -- United States -- 20th century.; Painters -- United States.; Painting, American -- 20th century.; Sculptors -- United States.; Sculpture, American -- 20th century.; Correspondence.; Essays.; Photographs.; Artists.; Painters.; Sculptors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Art projects
  - Mattatuck Historical Society, Waterbury, Connecticut, 1925-1965 (Box 1)
  - Elks National Memorial, Chicago, Illinois, 1926-1930 (Box 1)
  - Grand Army Plaza Fountain, Brooklyn, New York, 1930-1931 (Box 1)
  - Texas Centennial Memorial, 1936 (Box 1)
  - Fountain County Courthouse, Covington, Indiana, 1940-1965 (Box 1)
  - United States War Memorial, Epinal, France, 1948-1956; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Queens County Courthouse, Queens, New York, 1953-1963 (Box 1)
  - Centennial of the Land Grant College, Purdue University, Lafayette, Indiana, 1957-1961 (Box 2)
  - Court of Appeals Dome, Albany, New York, 1958-1959 (Box 2)
  - House of Representatives, Indianapolis, Indiana, 1961-1963 (Box 2)
  - First National City Bank of New York, New York, New York, 1961-1964 (Box 2)
  - Fifth Avenue Presbyterian Church Narthex, New York, New York, 1963-1964 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous projects, 1915; 1920-1921,; 1923,; 1934-1935,; 1940-1941,; 1943,; 1954,; 1957,; 1959-1966,; undated; 2 folders (Box 2)
- Biographical material
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- Writings
  - "Triumph of Conation" (Box 2)